The דף daf is ע"א, ayin aleph, excuse me, ע"ב, ayin bet,
72, but we pick up on the bottom of ע"א ayin aleph
on עמוד ב. amud bet. Just a little wrap up from yesterday,
this will only actually be a few lines. We had seen that
there's a question about what types of things you can cut before
the עומר Omer and one of the things was if it's not
really considered a harvesting of grain, but it is just a cutting
the weed for the grain, whatever the grain is for שחת, shachat,
for fodder. And this was debated in the משנה, Mishna, whether it
had to be when it began cutting when it was less than
a third ripe, which is clearly animal food, or even when it
was a third ripe. And this was then related to רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir who says a similar issue when one cuts for fodder
in the middle of a field, it divides the field into two
for פאה. pe'ah. It's not considered to be the beginning of a
harvest, it's considered a different type of a cutting. And then the
גמרא Gemara is just trying to identify who רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
really holds like, because the difference is that in our משנה Mishna
it meant and emphasized that the cutting was done explicitly to feed
to the animals, and רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir didn't say that. Now
normally you would think that's what fodder is, but apparently there was
a sense of also you could use some type of fodder for
human purposes as well where you're not interested in the grain, you're
maybe interested more in the straw or something of that nature. So
it seems that מאיר Meir has a different position. So we're just
going to pick up with just finally identifying רבי מאיר'ס Rebbi Meir's
position and with that we'll wrap up. So the גמרא Gemara says
אלא, ela, it is 3, 4, 5, 9 lines from the bottom,
line starts with the word תני. tani. It says אלא כי אתא
רב דימי ela ki ata Rav Dimi when רב דימי Rav Dimi
came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael אמר רבי מאיר amar Rebbi Meir
he said in name of רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, אמר, amar, excuse
me, רבי מאיר בשיטת רבי עקיבא רבו אמרה, Rebbi Meir beshitat Rebbi
Akiva rabbo amrah, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir was going by רבי עקיבא,
Rebbi Akiva, his רבי. rebbi.
Who was his רבי? rebbi?
Well, wasn't his only רבי. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Rabbi Akiva was the
רבי rebbi. he could take credit for, or could take credit for
him publicly, publicly, right, he could publicly acknowledge, exactly. No, רבי עקיבא
Rebbi Akiva was the רבי rebbi of the גמרא Gemara says all
of the major תנאים Tannaim in the משנה, Mishna, רבי מאיר, Rebbi
Meir, רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, all of the
major תנאים Tannaim of the משנה Mishna were תלמידי רבי עקיבא. talmidei
Rebbi Akiva. Anyway, so רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva אמר, amar, who says
what?
דאמר, de'amar, whatever, דאפילו אדם נמי לא הוי קצירה, de'afilu adam nami
la havei ketzirah, that if you're cut for שחת shachat even for
human consumption, it's not considered a harvesting. Where do we see this?
דתנן, detnan, well, that is what we're saying
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir said, המנמר שדה, hamenamer sadeh, if you leopard
a field, it means you spot it, you make little spots, you
cut different sections of it and it's spotted, ושיאר בה קלחים קלחים.
vishi'er bah kelachim kelachim. And again, this is a question, now do
you have multiple little fields left and you take a separate פאה
pe'ah for each or is it still one big field?
So there are left there קלחים, kelachim, which are like a shock
or whatever, moist stalks are left,
but the idea that they are קלחים kelachim means that they're not
yet ready to be harvested. So it means that what you harvested
was also not fully ready to be harvested. And so the assumption
here is that it was not being done for the, again, it
was being done essentially for type of a fodder because you did
it early, right, the stuff had not yet ripened. So רבי עקיבא
אומר פאה לכל אחד ואחד, Rebbi Akiva omer pe'ah lechol echad ve'echad,
each one is פאה pe'ah meaning they're considered separate sections, it's not
one big section. It's not considered an act of harvesting and it
therefore is considered like you have now separate
sections, a huge field and you're doing it.
So it could be, doesn't matter, וחכמים אומרים מאחד על הכל. vachachamim
omrim me'echad al hakol.
No, it's still one big field. But now and we qualified this,
דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, de'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda said in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, לא חייב רבי
עקיבא אלא במנמר לקליות. lo chiyev Rebbi Akiva ela bemenamer lekaliyot. רבי
עקיבא Rebbi Akiva only said that that was when you were spotting
it for קליות kaliyot and קליות kaliyot is again like a type
of a roasted
grain so you're going to make it roasted.
But what does this contrast to? אבל במנמר לאוצר לא, aval bemenamer
le'otzar lo,
not when you are doing it for storage. So presumably the difference
is, again, it's a little hard to understand exactly how the גמרא
Gemara compares this to the earlier debate, but רש"י Rashi says that
if it's לקליות lekaliyot means you're only going to be able to
eat it roasted, it was like we said before, which is when
the grain had not yet gotten to a third ripe. So there's
an assumption that this idea of cutting it and using it for
the roasted grain means the grain wasn't a third ripe and that
parallels what we said before that it's for fodder, but
human fodder maybe, but still considered fodder. And אוצר otzar means you're
going to store it which means the grain is ripe and that
would not be, that would just be the beginning of the harvest.
So the גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, is that really true? וכי
במנמר לאוצר לא? vechi bemenamer le'otzar lo?
If you do it spotted, then everyone agrees that if it's,
not everyone agrees,
no, that if
it's ready, then it's the beginning of the harvest process and right,
you only take one פאה. pe'ah. Right. The basic rule here is
that your cutting cannot make the field separate sections if it's the
beginning of just the harvesting. Then you're just cutting the field, right?
So it's only if it's not considered harvest which we are saying
now means קליות kaliyot which somehow means that it is, you can
only use the grain to roast it which is not really ripe,
you can only use it in some type of a special dish
and therefore it is considered for
fodder.
Pretty hard for anyone to find it, I mean if these look
like...
That is true. That is true. איני? Eini? So the גמרא Gemara
says, is this really true? והא כי אתא רבין אמר רבי יוחנן,
ve-ha ki ata Ravin amar Rabbi Yochanan, when רבין Ravin came from
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, he said in the name of
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, מחייב היה רבי מאיר אף במנא לאוצר, Mechayev
hayah Rabbi Meir af be-mana le-otzar, that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said
his position even when you're doing it for storage, which would be
like our case of asra a third, the grain really is ripe.
So again, maybe it's not fully being harvested as grain, maybe it's
being harvested as again fodder, again I don't really understand the fully
the difference, but okay, but it's not treated yet as grain, but
still even if it's considered ripe, he was say his position? So
the גמרא Gemara says, all right, you're right. סבר לה כוותיה בחדא
ופליג עליה בחדא. savar lah kavateih be-chada u-falig aleih be-chada. You're right.
רבי rebbi רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva went so far to say that
anything done for fodder no matter how much it's complete would be
considered a non-harvesting and break up the field. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
agrees with one point when it's less than fully ripe and he
does not agree with the other point or not fully when it's
less than ripe it's less than a third and not when it
is ripe. So that was a little complicated, it was wrapping up
from yesterday, but again the point is that if you're cutting for
fodder it is not considered a cutting, the relevance is that you
can do it before the עומר Omer is cut and here by
פאה Pe'ah the relevance is that it would break up the field
it would not be considered the beginning of the process the question
just become how do you define for fodder what's your intention whether
objectively the grain is a third ripe or not a third ripe
whether it's being done for humans or for animals all of these
are the various factors that play out. Now we continue with a
new but related topic, top of עין ב עמוד א. Ayin Bet
amud Aleph. הקוצר מפני הנטיעות ומפני בית האבל ומפני בית המדרש. ha-kotzer
mipnei ha-netiot u-mipnei beit ha-avel u-mipnei beit ha-midrash. So this is a
different type of cutting what does of harvesting I should say which
is allowed before the עומר Omer to set right once the once
the עומר Omer starts you're not allowed to cut get hear it
of anyway all right so I realize I've been saying cutting you
can harvest harvesting
because for the sake of these things this is permissible as we'll
see because they're considered harvesting for a מצוה mitzvah purpose and therefore
not for your purpose and for eating purpose and therefore it's not
prohibited before the עומר. Omer. So the reasons are מפני הנטיעות mipnei
ha-netiot means that they're growing together with shoots of trees so it's
a כלאים kilayim problem so you're cutting it down so it shouldn't
be כלאים kilayim and בית האבל ובית המדרש beit ha-avel u-beit ha-midrash
is that you want to clear space in a wheat field in
order that there should be a place for people to use of
it as a yard let's say they want to use it because
they that's where they want to sort of sit and do a
תנחומי אבלים tanchumei avelim that they used to do right after the
funeral in in some type of a of a חצר chatzer of
a of a yard outside of the of the בית הקברות beit
ha-kevarot or בית המדרש beit ha-midrash is you're just looking for an
open space to sit and have a study hall so you know
you had these huge wheat fields so you would cut down a
section of the wheat and you'd use some open space in that
type of a case that is not a harvesting for eating it
is a harvesting for a מצוה mitzvah purpose and therefore it's allowed
before the עומר. Omer. Let me just read and then you have
a comment. מאי טעמא mai ta'ama what's the reason says the גמרא?
Gemara? קצירכם אמר רחמנא ולא קציר מצוה. ketzirchem amar Rachmana ve-lo ketzir
mitzvah.
Well
that was easy. David says it says you shall it should be
ראשית קצירכם reshit ketzirchem the עומר Omer has to be the first
of your cuttings that we know you can't cut before the עומר
Omer because the עומר Omer has to be the first of the
first of the cuttings of your cuttings cuttings that are done to
serve your sort of mundane purposes but not in the sense of
the sake of a מצוה mitzvah to serve a divine purpose a
religious purpose that is not in the same category. Now you could
have the גמרא Gemara does do that sometimes it excludes things that
are done for the sake of a מצוה mitzvah
in a maybe not exactly parallel example but since it's ערב שבת
Erev Shabbat maybe we'll throw it out you know there's a idea
about we actually say in the it's one of the what do
you call it in the זמירות Zemiros right חפצך אסורים וגם מחשבות
cheftzecha asurim ve-gam machshavot right and then what was it לשדך הבנות
le-shadach ha-banot so anyway לשדך הבנות le-shadach ha-banot ותינוק ללמדו ספר ve-tinok
le-lamdo sefer anyway the גמרא Gemara says because it's you know it
says it's basically you can't do מצוא חפצך ודבר דבר metzo cheftzecha
ve-daber davar חפצך אסור חפצי שמים מותרים. cheftzecha asur cheftzei shamayim muttarim.
So you can talk about religious things even if those they're about
planning for after שבת Shabbat but like arranging for a kids you
know tutoring and teaching in תורה Torah whatever these types of things
חפצי שמים מותרים cheftzei shamayim muttarim it's why the שול shul is
allowed the you know is allowed to make announcements about events that
are after שבת Shabbat because it's under the broader under the umbrella
of חפצי שמים. cheftzei shamayim. The bingo game will be at exactly.
So anyway in various places now admittedly that's a kind of biblical
issue but nevertheless in various places the גמרא Gemara makes this distinction
between yours as opposed to sort of religious another good example I
should throw out is the basic principle we have עוסק במצוה פטור
מן המצוה osek be-mitzvah patur min ha-mitzvah we learn that from that
because it says by קריאת שמע Kriyat Shema it says you should
do it בשבתך בביתך ובלכתך בדרך ובשכבך ובקומך. be-shivtecha be-veitecha u-ve-lechtecha va-derech
u-ve-shachbecha u-ve-kumecha. I'm sorry,
ובשבתך בביתך ובלכתך בדרך ובשכבך ובקומך. u-ve-shivtecha be-veitecha u-ve-lechtecha va-derech u-ve-shachbecha u-ve-kumecha.
So it says ובלכתך בדרך u-ve-lechtecha va-derech when you're going about your
purposes but when you're going about you know religious purposes if you're
doing a מצוה mitzvah then you don't have a then you don't
have to say שמע Shema because עוסק במצוה פטור מן המצוה. osek
be-mitzvah patur min ha-mitzvah. So this is a general type of a
דרשה derashah the גמרא Gemara makes to exclude when you're doing types
of מצוה mitzvah related things but the thing that should be pointed
out is here you don't really have to put it in the
same category once you're saying that like if it's being done for
fodder it's not considered a harvesting you could be say here you're
not trying to get to use the wheat at all the grain
at all. You're just trying to get rid of it so that
you can use the space or so that it doesn't create כלאים.
kilayim. So you could have maybe even argued that it's not even
based on the מצווה mitzvah purpose, it's based on the part that
you're not interested in this as a way of getting grain, you're
just interested in a way of this as clearing the space. So
I'd point that out as that's another aspect of what is going
on here. You had a question.
Yeah, my question is, what do you do when these two things
conflict? If you're doing it totally for eating but then you give
the whole thing to the poor. Then can you do that? Because
then it's not... it's for a מצווה. mitzvah. I mean, you can't
think of a better מצווה mitzvah than that.
That's a good point, which also raises again the question about whether
you would have framed it as a מצווה mitzvah after what I
was saying as non-eating. After what I was saying, right. It's a
good question. It really depends on which aspect of those you emphasize.
And then let's say it's not for eating but it's הקדש, hekdesh,
then it's not mine and it would be totally okay for a
reason I needed to.
Yeah, that's a good point too. Presumably although if it was the
field owned by הקדש hekdesh by the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, we
would be able to harvest, although that's an excellent point, although that's
not being addressed here. Yeah. Okay, yeah, no I'm really... yeah, yeah,
I'll see if I can find that out. Now again, it's not
like, well actually, I mean it is
למעשה. l'maaseh. Yeah, that's interesting when you're not... I mean we know
that the איסור חדש issur chadash applies nowadays of eating, but this...
that's actually a very good question which I'll have to look up,
do they do that in ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? The איסור חדש
issur chadash applies nowadays because it doesn't matter about the bringing of
the עומר Omer or not, we started the גמרא Gemara learning it
out that the איסור חדש issur chadash applies even when there is
no עומר Omer and the sixteenth of ניסן Nissan is מתיר. mattir.
But since this is based on defining the עומר's Omer ראשית קצירכם,
reshit ketzirchem, notice the גמרא Gemara never spoke about what's מתיר קצירה
שלא בזמן העומר. mattir katzirah shelo b'zman haOmer. But presumably it's not
forbidden שלא בזמן העומר, shelo b'zman haOmer, because the whole prohibition of
קצירה katzirah is in order to define the עומר's Omer ראשית קצירכם.
reshit ketzirchem. If you don't have an עומר, Omer, so that's a
good question if any, but presumably there's no איסור קצירה בזמן הזה.
issur katzirah b'zman ha-zeh. I'd have to see. I mean it is
relevant, I don't know what they do in ישראל Yisrael if anybody...
if it ever comes up, but presumably there would be no איסור
קצירה בזמן הזה. issur katzirah b'zman ha-zeh. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, ולא יעשה כריכות אלא מניחם צבתים. v'lo ya'aseh
krichot ela manicham tzvatim. When we do allow you to do these
various things, whether it's for fodder or other things, since you're doing
it before the cutting of the עומר, Omer, don't make a big
production out of it. Don't make bundles, make it more like in
little piles. So מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? Says the
גמרא Gemara דכמה דאפשר לא טרחינן. d'chama d'efshar lo tarchinan. As much
as possible we don't want to put in the effort. I sort
of said make a big production, I'm focused on the publicity aspect,
but I think it's the same point. You don't want to start
really being invested in the process of harvesting too much before the
עומר. Omer. Some things are necessary, we'll let you do it, but
we don't really want to begin the whole harvesting process before the
עומר. Omer. Okay, מצות העומר להביא מן הקמה. Mitzvat haOmer l'havi min
hakama. Now the עומר Omer ideally should be brought from the standing
grain. That's what we've been talking, you harvest standing grain for the
sake of the עומר. Omer. But the משנה Mishnah goes on and
says if you did not cut any standing grain for the עומר,
Omer, then and some people obviously may be in prohibition, but whatever
it was, whether permissibly or not permissibly already cut grain, not for
the sake of the עומר, Omer, and you didn't get around to
cutting grain for the עומר, Omer, you can use already cut grain.
Okay, that's what the משנה Mishnah says. So now let's take a
look at the גמרא, Gemara, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. ואם תקריב מנחת
ביכורים. v'im takriv minchat bikurim. If you bring a...
the מנחה mincha of the first fruit, which is talking about the
שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem. So מה תלמוד לומר, mah talmud lomar, what
is this talking about? לפי... lefi... I'm sorry, no, it's talking about
the עומר, Omer, not
the
שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem. So here מנחת ביכורים minchat bikurim is referring
to the
עומר. Omer. So it says, so what's the verse teaching? לפי שמצות
העומר להביא מן הקמה. lefi shemitzvhat haOmer l'havi min hakama. The מצווה
mitzvah ideally is to bring it from the standing grain, to harvest
standing grain for the sake of the עומר. Omer. מניין שאם לא
מצא מן הקמה יביא מן העומרין? Minayin she'im lo matza min hakama
yavi min ha'omarim?
How do you know that if you did not find standing grain
that you could use for whatever reason, you can bring from the
sheaves, from grain that was already cut? And parenthetically we'll note that
that probably was done באיסור b'issur based on what we've just talked,
right, but okay. Either way, תלמוד לומר תקריב. talmud lomar takriv. So
it says ואם תקריב, v'im takriv, so the end of the פסוק
pasuk says, here's the whole פסוק pasuk says, ואם תקריב מנחת ביכורים
לה' אביב קלוי באש גרש כרמל תקריב את מנחת ביכוריך. v'im takriv
minchat bikurim l'Hashem aviv kalui ba'eish geres karmel takriv et minchat bikurecha.
So why did it have to say the verb twice? If you
bring, you shall bring. So the גמרא Gemara understands that the repetition
of the verb at the end of the פסוק pasuk of תקריב
takriv is telling you under any circumstances you can bring. Just make
sure that you bring. We really don't care how you get it,
just bring it. Okay,
so that's the emphasis of תקריב. takriv. Okay, תלמוד לומר תקריב. talmud
lomar takriv. דבר אחר, Davar acher, שאם לא מצא מן הלח יביא
מן היבש. she'im lo matza min halach yavi min hayavesh. The עומר
Omer ideally should be fresh. How do you know that if you
can't, you can bring dry? Again, it has to be this year's,
but it could be even dry. תלמוד לומר תקריב. talmud lomar takriv.
Just bring it. דבר אחר תקריב, Davar acher takriv, just bring it.
לפי שמצותו לקצור בלילה. Lefi shemitzvato liktzor balaila. It's supposed to do
it at night because of that makes תמימות, temimot, right, the full
seven weeks that it started at night. מניין שאם נקצר ביום כשר?
Minayin she'niktzar bayom kasher? How do you know that it's good if
you bring it at the day? So תלמוד לומר talmud lomar and
some say before it gets to that תקריב takriv another point. How
do you know ודוחה את השבת, v'docheh et haShabbat, also that it
overrides שבת? Shabbat? תלמוד לומר תקריב, Talmud lomar takriv, just bring it.
תקריב כל שהוא, Takriv kol shehu, bring whatever you can find, meaning
even if it's in the sheaf. תקריב מכל מקום. Takriv mikol makom.
Now מכל מקום mikol makom is interesting, especially when it's abbreviated, normally
that's an idiom which just means regardless. Regardless of whatever the problem
is, just bring it. But רש"י Rashi says מכל מקום mikol makom
here means literal, from any place in ישראל. Yisrael. So מכל מקום
mikol makom from any place. מכל מקום. mikol makom. Okay, so anyway
bring it but what's funny because that wasn't mentioned in the concerns
above. Okay, but be that as it may, bring it no matter
what, bring it from any place. תקריב אפילו בשבת, Takriv afilu b'Shabbat,
bring it even if it's on שבת, Shabbat, it overrides שבת. Shabbat.
And then once it's overriding שבת, Shabbat, תקריב אפילו בטומאה, Takriv afilu
b'tumah, bring it even if it's טמא. tamei. Again, this is a
fixed time communal sacrifice and fixed time communal sacrifices
override שבת. Shabbat. Okay, now we're going to look at the question
about whether it actually is can be cut during the day or
not, which our משנה Mishna said it could and this ברייתא Braita
just said it could but now that's going to be challenged. Let's
take a look. נקצר ביום כשר, Niktzar bayom kasher, if it was
cut during the day it's kosher. והתנן, V'hatnan, don't we teach in
a משנה, Mishna, this is in מגילה Megilla where it lists things
that have can only be done at day and things that only
can things that the מצוות mitzvot in the day and things that
the מצוות mitzvot at night and here's what we're saying in the
משנה. Mishna. כל הלילה כשר לקצירת העומר, Kol halaila kasher l'ktzirat ha'omer,
the entire night is kosher for the harvesting of the עומר omer
ולהקטיר חלבין ואיברים u'lehaktir chalavin v'evarim and to burning innards of a
קרבן. korban. זה הכלל Ze haklal says the משנה Mishna over there,
דבר שמצותו ביום davar shemitzva'to bayom anything that is a day מצוה,
mitzva,
כשר כל היום kasher kol hayom can be done the entire day.
דבר שמצותו בלילה Davar shemitzva'to balaila anything that's a night מצוה, mitzva,
כשר כל הלילה kasher kol halaila can be done the entire night.
So that's really coming to tell you you have the whole day
to do it, the whole night to do it. But the question
is also when don't you have when can you not do it?
And the implication is only during the day if it's a day
מצוה, mitzva, only during the night but not during the other time
period. And that's what the גמרא Gemara says.
קתני לילה דומיא דיום. Katani laila dumya d'yom. We taught night similar
to day. מה יום בלילה לא, Ma yom balaila lo, the same
way you know that day מצוות mitzvot cannot be done at night,
for example you can't take לולב lulav at night, that's a day
מצוה mitzva so day מצוות mitzvot cannot be done at night. So
similarly מה יום בלילה לא אף לילה ביום נמי לא. ma yom
balaila lo af laila bayom nami lo. So nighttime also a night
מצוה mitzva
you can't do during the day. So therefore if the עומר omer
were being told is a night מצוה mitzva then that means you
can't do it during the day. So how could our משנה Mishna
say that you can do it during the day?
When they say the day do they mean the following day or
the day before?
Excellent question. So תוספות Tosafot says well what do you mean, one
of the night מצוות mitzvot mentioned there is the burning of the
innards and that can be done the day before. So תוספות Tosafot
says okay so what we mean the day after. But actually he
says by the עומר omer really would it matter because the day
before really doesn't even begin to be the right time yet? So
by the עומר omer it's clear that the day before is off
limit and our question is about the day after.
Oh, but then it's more than תמימות, temimot, which means that the
question gets even better. In other words, it has to be at
least תמימות temimot and not earlier, but it certainly you know, in
other words, it's less of a problem if you're you know whether
having a baby that's born later than a preemie, you know what
I'm saying? So then so then
what's the question? I mean meaning why wouldn't you say that the
nighttime is like the earliest limit?
Because the דיוק diyuk of the משנה Mishna there is that it
is that the same way when we talk about day מצוות mitzvot
we don't say that I can do a day מצוה mitzva I
can do it the following night, I do it only during the
day. So if I'm calling it a night מצוה mitzva presumably it
means only during the night and not the day.
Or maybe there's some that are you know sort of like a
hybrid list, some are only... right.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara is coming to דייק dayek that
you could say that in the משנה Mishna there but that's what
the גמרא Gemara is trying to suggest to say the same way
it would never occur to you that anything on the day list
could be done at night and we intuitively understand that day מצוות
mitzvot are only for the day, we are going to assume that
the same thing is true about the list of night מצוות. mitzvot.
Now you say I don't know, night מצוות mitzvot are pretty rare
so maybe a night מצוה mitzva starts at night but continues in
the day. Okay, so that's what that is a reasonable read but
that's why גמרא Gemara is making it explicit that that's not how
it's choosing to read the משנה. Mishna.
That won't change its mind I guess?
Exactly, it's not going to change its mind here the question is
how are we going to פסקן? pasken? It's going to see that
it's a debate and the question is going to be how we're
going to פסקן. pasken. Victor you had a question.
Why is it practical to cut the עומר omer at night?
Not practical. You need a lot of torches. But then you're not
cutting so much so you don't need to do any process. But
the גמרא Gemara learns it from the idea of תמימות. temimot. But
you're right, it's not so practical, but תוספות Tosafot imagines that it's
like an עומר omer and it doesn't rain. No, that's a good
point, it's a full moon. Imagine that it's like a nice event
right? Everybody you know goes out right right after מוצאי יום טוב,
Motzaei Yom Tov, a lot of torches, big big deal. But anyway
the point is I don't know if it's practical but the גמרא
Gemara learns it from תמימות. temimot. Okay, so anyway, all right, so
now let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara chooses to read
this list that it's only a night מצוה mitzva and our משנה
Mishna said that you can do it in the day.
So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא Rava
says לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא רבי והא רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Ha Rebbi v'ha Rebbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon, it's a
debate between רבי Rebbi and רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rebbi Elazar b'Rabbi
Shimon. דתניא, D'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Braita, היה עומד ומקריב
מנחת העומר. Haya omed u'makriv Minchat Ha'omer. Okay, so the כהן kohen
was there bringing the מנחת העומר Minchat Ha'omer ונטמאת, v'nitmet, and it
became טמא tamei as he was right about to put it on
the מזבח mizbe'ach and something happened, it became טמא. tamei. Okay, now
what do you do? So, so here's what you do. Now
remember we did say the עומר omer could be brought בטומאה, betumah,
but the question is you do have an alternative here perhaps, go
go back to the field and get some more. Okay so which
do you do? Okay now to some degree there's a question also
about to what degree when we say things are
מותר בציבור, mutar betzibur, טומאה הותרה בציבור, tumah hutra betzibur, does it
mean only if we've exhausted other opportunities or not? So I'm going
to bracket that and just assume that that we are going to
first try to try to exhaust other opportunities although that'll be a
question. Okay, so it became טמא. tamei. So what are you going
to do? אם יש אחרת, im yesh acheres, if you can bring
another, go get some more grain. אומר לו הבא אחרת תחתיה. omer
lo havei acheres tachte'ha. Stop, go get another עומר, omer, bring the
other grain. Let's do it again. Don't use the טמא tamei one.
ואם לאו, ve'im lav, if you cannot get other grain in time,
near the end of the day or whatever it is, there's no
other ripe grain, whatever the case might be. אומר לו, omer lo,
you say to the כהן, Kohen, הוי פיקח ושתוק. havei pike'ach ushtok.
Be smart and just keep it to yourself. Okay. דברי רבי אלעזר.
divrei Rabbi Elazar. That's רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. Oh no. Now רש"י
Rashi says why why why do we say שתוק? shtok? I mean
you know טומאה הותרה בציבור. tumah hutra betzibur. We don't say like
if קרבן פסח Korban Pesach people are טמא tamei let's not talk
about it. So why here do we say you know do we
say keep it quiet?
Is it because they don't talk about the fact that it's טמא?
tamei? So that's interesting. רש"י Rashi says is a concern that people
you know that that that people it'll mislead people. That people will
see oh look, a טמא tamei מנחה minchah was
brought, maybe you can bring טמא tamei מנחות. minchos. That's what רש"י
Rashi says the concern is. That it'll mislead people. Presumably it was
not as much of a concern by the other by other cases
because by other cases if you think about it, normally when you
have טומאה tumah a טומאה tumah problem, it's the animal became טמא
tamei normally you could just like bring another animal.
And maybe again, you know so normally a טומאה tumah problem was
when the people were טמא tamei and then it was well known
that that was an overrode consideration. Anyway I'm not exactly clear why
here we have to more keep it quiet than other places but
רש"י Rashi says the reason of keeping it quiet is not to
mislead people. That they'll think that מנחות minchos could be brought בטומאה
betumah and they won't realize it's specifically by the מנחת העומר minchas
haomer which is a communal and a fixed time קרבן. Korban.
That's what I'm saying. I mean they give a whole production where
it feels a little bit different than their regular מנחה. minchah. Right.
Why would people be מטעה? mat'eh? Yeah, I don't know. Right, I
mean you could try to speculate why it's somehow is more easily
confused with a private קרבן Korban than other קרבנות, Korbanos, but I'm
not really sure it works. Because you know other קרבנות Korbanos also
what made them so distinctive? I mean you're right there was a
whole production that preceded it. So it's not so clear what the
שתוק shtok is well it's clear what it's doing, it's not so
clear why here specifically we're supposed to be quiet. But basically bring
it anyway.
Bring it anyway.
Right. בטומאה מכל מקום. betumah mikal makom.
There you go.
Okay well that was בטומאה. betumah. דברי רבי אלעזר. divrei Rabbi Elazar.
That's what רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says.
But we don't do that for anything else.
רבי אלעזר ורבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar veRabbi Shimon say keep it quiet.
That but if everything else is טמא tamei we
If it's a fixed time קרבן Korban then then you do bring
it בטומאה. betumah. That's our general rule of טומאה הותרה בציבור. tumah
hutra betzibur. So this is not unique in that way but what
is strange is the use of the word שתוק. shtok. Normally we're
not quiet about it. We know that's the rule. It's overridden for
a קרבן ציבור. Korban tzibur. Okay. Anyway either way what he's saying
is try to bring another, if you can't bring another, bring this.
That's דברי רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. divrei Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon. That's
what דברי רבי. divrei Rebbe. I'm sorry. Thank you. דברי רבי. divrei
Rebbe. Say okay that's what רבי Rebbe says. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון
אומר, Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon omer, רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar
berabi Shimon says בין כך ובין כך, bein kach uvein kach, even
if you could bring another one, אומר לו הוי פיקח ושתוק. omer
lo havei pike'ach ushtok. Just bring it. Okay why? Why don't bring
another one? Here's why. שכל העומר שנקצר שלא כמצוותו פסול. shekol haomer
sheniktzar shelo kemitzvaso pasul.
It won't help you to go back into the field. Why won't
it help you to go back into the field? Because it's during
the day, it'll be שלא כמצוותה, shelo kemitzvasah, and it's פסול. pasul.
ביום זה פסול. bayom zeh pasul. No but that doesn't matter.
That that no that became that that like it was נפסל nifsal
but it wasn't that the cutting was wrong. Okay so it has
to be the right cutting of the עומר, omer, the cutting of
night which is the מצוה mitzvah to do it in order to
use it during the day. So here you say here look there's
this debate. According to רבי, Rebbe, if it's cut during the day
you can use it for a קרבן. Korban. According to רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון, Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon, if it's cut during the day
you can't use it for a קרבן. Korban. So רבי Rebbe is
our משנה, mishna, משנה mishna says if it's נקצר ביום niktzar bayom
it's כשר. kasher. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon is
the משנה במגילה mishna beMegillah that says the מצוה mitzvah is only
at night not during the day. Now I should point out that
while clearly there is this debate of whether בדיעבד bedi'eved it's כשר
kasher if it was cut during the day, you could have actually
said that even our משנה mishna agrees with the משנה במגילה mishna
beMegillah the way the גמרא Gemara reads משנה במגילה. mishna beMegillah. Because
you have to distinguish between whether the מצוה mitzvah was fulfilled and
what the status of the grain is. Right? You could have said
did I get my מצוה mitzvah points, did I get to do
the מצוה? mitzvah? Maybe you've only done the מצוה mitzvah by doing
it at night. Maybe when it's day it's not considered you did
the מצוה mitzvah of cutting the עומר, omer, right?
But even if I didn't do the מצוה, mitzvah, I didn't do
it correctly, maybe the grain could still be used for the קרבן.
Korban. So the question of whether the grain and that's actually what
the way the גמרא Gemara frames it. The way the גמרא Gemara
actually frames it is if it's done שלא כמצוותו shelo kemitzvaso is
it כשר kasher or not? Which assumes that it's שלא כמצוותו. shelo
kemitzvaso. And but the The question still is, okay, it was שלא
כמצוותו shelo k'mitzvaso but can I still use it? Okay, so really
the משנה מגילה Mishnah Megillah wants to know were you יוצא yotzei
the מצווה. mitzvah. That's one question. Maybe I wasn't יוצא yotzei the
מצווה. mitzvah. Our משנה Mishnah wants to know, can בדיעבד b'diavad you
use it? That's a different question if it was cutting in the
day. Anyway, the גמרא's Gemara emphasizing that even in the בדיעבד, b'diavad,
there's a debate between רבי Rebbi and רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rabbi
Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon, where רבי Rebbi says בדיעבד b'diavad you can use
grain that was cut during the day, and רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון
Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon says that you cannot. Okay, so now we
are going to see about that.
Yeah? Is like, you know, any of these things, I don't know
if there's like a hierarchy. From let's say you did it at
night but from בית השלוחים, Beis HaShluchim, then you know, you came
and said, oh wait, now it's the day but I found something
that's not מבית השלוחים m'Beis HaShluchim and it would...
Right. Right. That's a good question too. You're right. According to רבי
Rebbi that says בדיעבד b'diavad it's good, what the... what are the
different degrees of בדיעבד? b'diavad? There's also a בדיעבד b'diavad of בית
השלוחים, Beis HaShluchim, there's a בדיעבד b'diavad of day. Right, the degrees
of בדיעבד. b'diavad. There's a בדיעבד b'diavad of if it's not fresh,
if it's dry. Right, so you raise a good question. According to
רבי, Rebbi, how do you choose between the various בדיעבד? b'diavads? I
don't know the answer. But the first point is that whether the
בדיעבד b'diavad of day is good is a debate of רבי Rebbi
and רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon. I should also
say by the way that this תוספות Tosafot assumes that whatever the
question is of when you start the עומר, Omer, is also whether
you can start it night or whether you cut it at night
or you can even cut it during the day is also the
question of the מצווה mitzvah of counting the עומר, Omer, ספירת העומר.
Sefirat HaOmer. That if you're allowed to cut it in the day
and that could be כשר kasher like רבי, Rebbi, then you're allowed
to do the מצווה mitzvah ספירת העומר Sefirat HaOmer during the day.
If you're allowed if you could only cut the עומר Omer at
night and it's not good during the day then you can't do
the ספירת העומר Sefirat HaOmer and the day either, which is a
little bizarre because that's the next 48 days, it's not just the
start. But nevertheless תוספות Tosafot thinks that they're interdependent. תוספות Tosafot thinks
we rule like the משנה Mishnah of מגילה, Megillah, which says that
it's only a night מצווה mitzvah not a day מצווה, mitzvah, which
means בדיעבד b'diavad it's not good during the day. And therefore תוספות
Tosafot says בדיעבד b'diavad you can't do ספירת העומר... Sefirat HaOmer... even
בדיעבד b'diavad you can't do ספירת העומר Sefirat HaOmer during the day.
Luckily he also says that even if you miss a day you
can count the next day. So it's not so terrible. But anyway
תוספות Tosafot ties this into the question of ספירת העומר. Sefirat HaOmer.
Let's go back to the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbah bar
bar Chanah amar Rabbi Yochanan. So רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar
bar Chanah says in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון בשיטת רבי עקיבא רבו של אביו אמרה. Rabbi Elazar
b'Rabbi Shimon b'shitat Rabbi Akiva rabo shel aviv amrah. So we're doing
a lot of this. We just did it with רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir and רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, here we're doing רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון. Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon. So רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar is the
son of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is
one of the students of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Actually it's רבי
שמעון בר יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, which I mentioned because we're
right at the cusp of ל"ג בעומר. Lag BaOmer. So might as
well mention רבי שמעון בר יוחאי. Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. Okay, so
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon said in the name
of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, who was his father's, רבי שמעון's, Rabbi
Shimon רבי. Rebbi. Okay, it says רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was רבי
שמעון's Rabbi Shimon רבי. Rebbi. So what is רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva
position that ties into רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון? Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon?
רבי שמעון אמר. Rabbi Shimon amar. Where am I?
דתנן. D'tenan. We taught in the משנה. Mishnah. כלל אמר רבי עקיבא.
Klall amar Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said a general principle.
כל מלאכה שאפשר לה לעשות מערב שבת אינה דוחה את השבת. Kol
melachah she'efshar lah l'asot m'erev Shabbos einah docha es haShabbos. Any מלאכה
melachah that can be done before שבת Shabbos does not override שבת.
Shabbos. Now he was saying this by the idea of can מילה
milah override שבת. Shabbos. But how about if you had to get
the מכשירי מילה, machshirei milah, you had to sharpen the scalpel, you
had to bring it to the place where you were going to
do the ברית מילה, bris milah, that doesn't override שבת, Shabbos, that
could be done before. Okay. Now the גמרא's Gemara going to assume
that this means, although you can easily distinguish, means any time any
thing could... any part could have been done before, then you don't
do it on שבת Shabbos even if that part is actually a
מצווה mitzvah to do today. Which means the cutting of the עומר.
Omer. Can the עומר Omer be cut on שבת Shabbos if the
16th of ניסן Nissan is שבת? Shabbos? The משנה Mishnah says yes,
the ברייתא Baraisa say yes, we of course assume the answer is
yes. The question is, why yes? Why not do it, you know,
the day before? Well the day before's יום טוב. Yom Tov. Why
not do it two days before? And get it ready? Why do
it on שבת? Shabbos? So the easy answer is, okay, even if
בדיעבד b'diavad it was כשר kasher if I did it two or
three days before, the מצווה's mitzvah to do it on, you know,
ממחרת השבת. mimacharat haShabbat. It's not like the מכשירי מילה, machshirei milah,
which I should have done before and there's no מצווה mitzvah to
do on שבת. Shabbos. Here the מצווה mitzvah to do it is
on the 16th. But the גמרא Gemara for now puts that in
the same category as sharpening the scalpel and says if it would
have been כשר kasher if you had done it before, then according
to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, you should be cutting the עומר Omer
before שבת. Shabbos. So why don't you when the 16th falls out
on שבת? Shabbos? That's the question. Let's take a look.
Okay. וסבר לה כרבי ישמעאל. V'savar lah k'Rabbi Yishmael. And רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon also took like רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi
Yishmael. What does רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael say? דאמר קצירת העומר מצווה.
D'amar kzirat haOmer mitzvah. That קצירת העומר kzirat haOmer is a מצווה.
mitzvah. Now it doesn't just mean a מצווה, mitzvah, but it's also
a מצווה mitzvah that overrides שבת. Shabbat. דתנן, D'tenan, we taught in
the משנה. Mishnah. רבי ישמעאל אומר. Rabbi Yishmael omer. מה חריש רשות
אף קציר רשות. Mah charish reshut af katzir reshut. The same way
harvesting is always... excuse me, plowing is always optional, also harvesting, the
harvesting that's forbidden on שבת Shabbat is optional, is the type of
harvesting that is optional. What is that about? חרישה? Charisha? No, שבת.
Shabbat. He's talking about the פסוק pasuk that says in
משפטים, Mishpatim, ששת ימים... Sheshet yamim... what is it... ששת ימים תעבוד
וביום השביעי תשבות בחריש ובקציר
תשבות. Sheshet yamim ta'avod u'vayom hashvi'i tishbot becharish u'vekatzir tishbot. Okay, in
your plowing and in your harvesting you shall rest. So he says,
oh, what type of harvesting do you have to rest for on
שבת? Shabbat? This harvesting that's like the plowing, when it's optional. What
does that exclude? יצא קצירת העומר שהיא מצווה. Yatza kzirat haOmer she'hi
mitzvah. To exclude the cutting of the עומר Omer that's a
מצווה. mitzvah. of that is, he says that you harvest the עומר
omer on שבת. Shabbat. So where are we? We have a statement
that you harvest the עומר omer on שבת, Shabbat, that we knew,
that's in our משנה. mishnah. I wonder why he had to go
to רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. We also have a statement that if
it could have been done before שבת, Shabbat, then you should do
it before שבת. Shabbat. So now the question is well why then
does harvesting override שבת? Shabbat? Why not do it before שבת? Shabbat?
So let's take a look. Okay. ואי סלקא דעתך נקצר שלא כמצותו
כשר. ve-i salka da'atach niktzar she-lo ke-mitzvato kasher. So this is רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar Berabbi Shimon's proof that you cannot do
something not exactly the right way because if you were to say
that when you cut it in the wrong time שלא כמצותו, she-lo
ke-mitzvato, it would still be good, אמאי דחי שבת? amai dachi Shabbat?
Why do we have the principle that cutting the עומר omer overrides
שבת? Shabbat? נקצריה מערב שבת. niktzereyah m'erev Shabbat. Let's do it ערב
שבת, erev Shabbat, not really ערב שבת erev Shabbat which is יום
טוב, Yom Tov, but okay, two days before. אלא מדי דחי שבת,
ella mi-de-dachi Shabbat, since we have the principle that cutting the עומר
omer overrides
שבת, Shabbat, שמע מינה נקצר שלא כמצותו פסול. shma mina niktzar she-lo
ke-mitzvato pasul. Obviously if you would have done it any other time
it would be invalid. So here's what the גמרא Gemara's saying how
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar Berabbi Shimon got his idea that
if you do it any time that's not the exact right מצוה
mitzvah time, it's invalid. Because we know the עומר omer overrides שבת.
Shabbat. We also but okay, but why still? It shouldn't override שבת
Shabbat if you had another option, so why not cut it from
before שבת? Shabbat? It must be that if you cut it at
the time that is not exactly when the תורה Torah designates, it's
not good. And if that's true the second you can't cut it
before then it's also true that you can't cut it after the
night, you can't cut it in the day. That's also not the
exact time the תורה Torah designates. The exact time the תורה Torah
designates is the night of the sixteenth and from this we learn
that any time other than that, either before or after, is invalid
because if it were valid you would just have done it before
and you would not have had it override שבת. Shabbat. Okay, that's
how the גמרא Gemara argues it. Obviously there are ways you could
just debate all of that, say maybe before is different than after.
This is you know this is different than the מילה milah case,
but that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying. So now the גמרא
Gemara says if that is such an obvious argument, how could רבי
Rabbi disagree with it? How could רבי Rabbi say that it is
good during the day? So the גמרא Gemara says ורבי לאו תלמידיה
דרבי שמעון הוא? ve-Rabbi lav talmideh de-Rabbi Shimon hu? You what do
you mean and רבי Rabbi is not a student of רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon meaning if רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar got it from his
father and his father got it from רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, רבי
Rabbi is also part of that chain.
Okay. How do you know?
דתניא, de-tanya, one minute, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, אמר רבי,
amar Rabbi, רבי Rabbi says, כשהיינו למודים תורה אצל רבי שמעון בתקוע,
kesheh-hayinu lomedim Torah etzel Rabbi Shimon be-Tekoa, when we were learning תורה
Torah by רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in תקוע. Tekoa. It's the whole
point of this quote now just to show that he's a student
of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון בר יוחאי
Rabbi
Shimon
Bar Yochai like I said right there near ל"ג בעומר Lag BaOmer
so you can try to find some mystical significance of all of
this. Anyway, היינו מעלים לו שמן ואלונטית, hayinu ma'alim lo shemen ve-alontit,
we used to bring him on שבת Shabbat oil and like a
towel, מחצר לגג, me-chatzer le-gag,
we would go from the courtyard to the roof, ומגג לקרפיף, u-me-gag
le-karfif, and from the roof to, forget what a קרפיף karfif is,
some other type of a yard, ומקרפיף לקרפיף אחר, u-mi-karfif le-karfif acher,
and
from one to another, עד שאנו מגיעים למעין שאנו רוחצים בו, ad
she-anu magiyim la-ma'ayan she-anu rochtzim bo,
until we could get to the well which we bathed ourselves in
on שבת. Shabbat. So first of all they're bathing themselves on שבת,
Shabbat, okay, but it wasn't water that was heated up on שבת.
Shabbat. That's not our interest right now. It is interesting but nowadays
אשכנזים Ashkenazim have a מנהג minhag not to fully immerse themselves in
water even cold water on שבת. Shabbat. Okay why we don't go
swimming on שבת, Shabbat, ספרדים Sefardim actually do, at least swimming in
the swimming pool whatever. Anyway we won't go into that right now.
But the other relevant point of this משנה, mishnah, of this of
this teaching is that all of this stuff was surrounded with like
walls, but the question is do you need to do a עירוב
חצרות? eruv chatzerot? Are they considered separate domains so that you need
to join them all together? You know when we do the עירוב
eruv around the city like we both have that the stuff around
the city we call it an עירוב eruv but it's really a
צורת הפתח. tzurat ha-petach. The עירוב eruv is really getting everybody to
contribute to a box of מצות matzos so it's all considered one
domain. The point of this teaching was to say there were those
that felt that roofs and courtyards and all these things were by
definition separate domains and had to be sort of unified and רבי
Rabbi is saying bringing this as evidence that it does not. We
could talk more of that in about six months, six years from
now when we get to עירובין, Eruvin, not six years, whatever three
years from now we get to עירובין. Eruvin. Anyway the point of
all of this is to show you that רבי Rabbi was a
student of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So if רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
is a student of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and really holds of
this idea that if you could do it before שבת, Shabbat, you
should do it before שבת, Shabbat, so why anyway does רבי Rabbi
not come to the same conclusion? The fact why do you have
the עומר omer override שבת, Shabbat, why not do it before? And
the conclusion that we've come to at least was must be that
any time that's not the right time is invalid. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says, and so what's the גמרא Gemara's answer? סבר לה
כאידך דרבי שמעון, savar lah ke-idach de-Rabbi Shimon, he holds like the
other position of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. דתניא, de-tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, braita, אמר רבי שמעון, amar Rabbi Shimon, רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon said, בא וראה כמה חביבה מצוה בשעתה, bo u-re'eh kama chaviva
mitzvah be-shat'ah, come see how dear is a מצוה mitzvah in its
right time, שהרי הקטר חלבים ואיברים כשרים כל הלילה, she-harei hakter chalavim
ve-eivarim ksherim kol ha-layla, you could burn the innards and the fats
of קרבנות korbanot at night, ולא היה ממתין לעשותן, ve-lo haya mamtin
la-asotan, and we did not wait till night. What is he talking
about? Any קרבן korban that's brought on שבת Shabbat and יום טוב,
Yom Tov, the מוסף, Musaf, the תמיד, Tamid, right, anything that's brought
on שבת Shabbat and יום טוב, Yom Tov, why do we burn
the fats that day? Why don't we say hey, you know Till
night. Why override שבת? shabbos? It says no, it's important to do
it at the right time not to postpone it even though it's
kosher at another time, and therefore we would override שבת. shabbos. So
this is directly relevant. Here he's saying that if this is the
time to do it, even if it's kosher at another time, it
still is important enough to override שבת. shabbos. And that's exactly our
case of the cutting of the עומר. Omer. You could say, you
know what, it is בדיעבד bedieved kosher if you did it earlier.
It is בדיעבד bedieved kosher if you did it later. But the
time is the nighttime of the sixteenth and therefore that overrides שבת.
shabbos. That's a very good argument. Okay. So and that's exactly, by
the way, why it's different than sharpening the scalpel for the ברית
מילה, Bris Milah, right, or carrying the knife, because there's no מצוה
mitzvah to do that on שבת. shabbos. That you should have done
beforehand. But if there's a מצוה mitzvah to do it today, even
if בדיעבד bedieved it could be kosher before or after, you do
it today. You do it on שבת. shabbos. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara is going to say that's such a good point, why
does ר' אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon not say that?
So let's turn now to the עמוד ב'. amud beis. ר' אלעזר
ברבי שמעון לא שמיע ליה. Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon lo shmiah lei.
What? So ר' אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon, he didn't
hear about this principle? I mean, it is his father. So you
know, so if that's true, there goes your whole proof that it's
invalid beforehand because you could totally say it's valid earlier or later
and still say it overrides שבת shabbos because this is the right
time. The right time is the sixteenth at night no matter if
it's kosher earlier or later. Okay. אלא שאני התם, Ela shani hasam,
he would say the case by the burning of the innards by
the קרבנות korbanos is not exactly the same. You can't bring proof
from there. Why? דחה שחיטה את השבת. dachsah shechitah es hashabbos. There
you started with you started with a license to violate שבת. shabbos.
When you bring your עולה olah on שבת, shabbos, your מוסף musaf
or whatever you're bringing, you are allowed to slaughter it and then
sprinkle the blood. That you have to do. Then you could say
oh, once you got started, finish up. Do all the rest of
the עבודות avodos of the קרבן korban today even though technically you
could leave some stuff over for tonight. But that's because we let
you get started. He says you can't learn from there that you
could allow something to start on שבת shabbos if it could be
done at a different time even if it's the best time to
do it is שבת. shabbos. So when it comes to cutting the
עומר, Omer, where we're questioning can we start on שבת, shabbos, there
I would say that if there's another time that would be kosher
even if the night is the better time, do it at the
other time. So this is again to focus us on what ר'
אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon is saying is, I mean
look, there's a fascinating question in itself, to when are the parameters
of how these types of בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash things override שבת?
shabbos? Is it only if they need to be done? Even if
they can be done at another time? So what we know from
the קרבן korban case is that if you're allowed to bring the
קרבן korban on שבת, shabbos, then you're allowed to finish it up
on שבת shabbos even though technically you could leave some stuff over
for after שבת. shabbos. The עומר Omer presents us with a case
where the מצוה mitzvah is to do it today, but it would
be kosher if it were done at another time. Can it still
override שבת? shabbos? רבי Rebbi says yes it can and you do
it on שבת. shabbos. ר' אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon
says actually if it would be kosher at another time, I would
say you're not allowed to do it. So then why does it
override שבת? shabbos? For me this is evidence that if you do
it at another time, it's not kosher בדיעבד. bedieved. And that's where
ר' אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon gets his position that
if you do it either too early or too late in the
day, בדיעבד bedieved it's no good. All right, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. That actually makes sense. You like that position
that you should better do it not on שבת shabbos if you
can? Yeah, yeah. No, that's a good theory. What? Yeah, a good
theory. No. Okay, yeah. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay, ולרבי, u'l'Rebbi, so רבי Rebbi says, ולרבי הכי נמי
דחה שחיטה את השבת, u'l'Rebbi hachi nami dachsah shechitah es hashabbos, so
the גמרא Gemara said ah, you make a very good distinction. So
that case about finishing up the קרבן korban is not good evidence
to the idea. There you actually started by giving you a license
to violate שבת. shabbos. It doesn't prove that we would let you
start violating שבת shabbos if it could be done at another time.
And now the גמרא Gemara is going to focus on this question.
We got ר' אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon. Here's the
question. רבי Rebbi says it's if it's in the day it's kosher,
right? How could he say that you could do it on שבת?
shabbos? If the גמרא Gemara is now saying, why not do it,
it's assuming that it's kosher in the daytime, it's kosher earlier, you
could debate that but that's what the גמרא Gemara is assuming. So
how could it override שבת? shabbos? Why not do it earlier? And
don't tell me oh, because the מצוה mitzvah is to do it
on שבת shabbos and therefore it's better that way. That's only when
you have an initial license to violate שבת shabbos like you started
to bring the קרבן. korban. Here where you're starting the process, if
it's possible even if it's a מצוה, mitzvah, if it's possible to
do it not on שבת, shabbos, you should do it not on
שבת. shabbos. So how does רבי Rebbi allow the cutting of the
עומר Omer to violate שבת shabbos if in theory according to him
it would be kosher earlier or later? So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא Ela makes a radical statement. אלא,
Ela, says the גמרא, Gemara, קסבר רבי לא דחיה שבת. kasavar Rebbi
lo dachya shabbos. You're right. That's such a good question I'm going
to have to say that רבי Rebbi holds that it does not
override שבת. shabbos. And now the גמרא Gemara is going to go
through and assume that רבי Rebbi holds against all the other evidence,
all the other statements, that cutting of the עומר Omer does not
override שבת. shabbos. ולא והתנן? v'lo v'hatnan? How about our משנה mishna
says? the sages said whether Shabbat or the weekday, you would bring
the עומר omer from three סאים. se'im. The גמרא Gemara says דלא
כרבי, d'lo k'Rebbe, fine, that's against רבי, Rebbe, רבי Rebbe would disagree.
Now another משנה, Mishnah, וחכמים אומרים אחד שבת ואחד חול בשלושה בשלוש
קופות ובשלושה מגלות. v'chachamim omrim echad Shabbat v'echad chol bishlosha bishalosh kupot
u'bishlosha magalot. I know, same משנה. Mishnah. The חכמים chachamim say whether
on שבת Shabbat or the weekday, you would have three people, three
baskets, three sieves. So you see it goes it violates it overrides
שבת. Shabbat. דלא כרבי, d'lo k'Rebbe, fine, that's not like רבי. Rebbe.
But how about our משנה? Mishnah? Or how about another משנה? Mishnah?
בשבת יאמר להם שבת זו b'Shabbat yomar lahem Shabbat zo? When they
go out and do the whole big, you know, טקס, tekes, the
whole big procedural there in cutting the עומר, omer, and it says
the guy lifts up his sieve and says shall I cut it
on שבת? Shabbat? And everybody says yes, cut it on שבת, Shabbat,
and then he cuts it. So you see they're making a big
to-do about it. דלא כרבי, d'lo k'Rebbe, fine, that's also not like
רבי, Rebbe, רבי Rebbe would say you don't do it on שבת.
Shabbat. It's amazing we have never heard explicitly any תנא tanna debate
this and based on the גמרא's Gemara own logic אגב דאיתקש, agav
d'itkash, if it's כשר kasher during the day it's כשר kasher on
שבת, Shabbat, they create a whole new position that there's the position
of רבי Rebbe that it doesn't violate שבת, Shabbat, it doesn't override
שבת. Shabbat. Now we're not done, our we go although חדתא chadata
it's probably is not a new point cause you'll see it continues.
The next part of our משנה Mishnah says נקצר ביום כשר ודוחה
את השבת. niktzar b'yom kasher v'doche et ha-Shabbat. If it's cut in
the day it's כשר kasher and it overrides שבת Shabbat and that
line itself is exactly the problem the גמרא's Gemara dealing with. If
it's כשר kasher during the day it's כשר kasher not at its
right time and so then you couldn't see we do it earlier
and nevertheless it says it overrides שבת. Shabbat. So here you have
the two positions that the גמרא Gemara says can't come together and
they're right there in our משנה. Mishnah. So the גמרא Gemara says
מאן סתם לה דאמר נקצר ביום כשר רבי. man stam lei de'amar
niktzar b'yom kasher Rebbe. That was רבי Rebbe based on our earlier
discussion. וקתני u'ktani and the very same משנה Mishnah says דוחה את
השבת. doche et ha-Shabbat. So and it overrides שבת. Shabbat. מאי לאו
קצירה mai lav k'tzirah? Isn't that the cutting overrides שבת? Shabbat? So
the גמרא Gemara says לא להקרבה. lo l'hakravah. Totally bizarre read of
the משנה, Mishnah, the entire משנה Mishnah was all talking about the
cutting of the עומר omer and it says this line where it
says it overrides שבת Shabbat is not talking about the cutting, it's
talking about the bringing of the עומר omer overrides שבת, Shabbat, not
the cutting. So the גמרא Gemara says אבל לקצירה לא aval l'k'tzirah
lo? You still want to insist that you can't do the cutting
of the עומר omer on שבת Shabbat according to רבי? Rebbe? והתניא,
v'hatanya, we learned in a ברייתא, baraita, רבי אומר, Rebbe omer, רבי
Rebbe says וידבר משה את מועדי השם. vayidaber Moshe et mo'adei Hashem.
משה Moshe spoke the holidays of God to בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael.
מה תלמוד לומר ma talmud lomar? Why does it have to say
he spoke this? I mean everything he gave over to בני ישראל.
Bnei Yisrael. לפי שלא למדנו אלא לתמיד ופסח, lefi she'lo lamadnu ela
l'Tamid u'Pesach, we only know in terms of things that override שבת
Shabbat and override טומאה, tumah, we only know it explicitly by the
קרבן תמיד korban Tamid and the קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. שנאמר בהם
shene'emar bahem it says by them במועדו, b'mo'ado, that it should be
brought in its right time במועדו, b'mo'ado, in its right time it
says one by תמיד, Tamid, one by פסח, Pesach, and from there
we learn ואפילו בשבת במועדו ואפילו בטומאה. v'afilu b'Shabbat b'mo'ado v'afilu b'tumah.
In its right time even if it overrides שבת, Shabbat, you bring
the תמיד Tamid and the פסח Pesach in the right time even
if there is a טומאה tumah problem. So that we know by
the תמיד Tamid and פסח. Pesach. שאר קרבנות הציבור מנין sha'ar korbanot
hatzibur minayin? How you know about other communal sacrifices that they also
override if they have fixed times, that is fixed time communal sacrifices
as override שבת Shabbat and override טומאה? tumah? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar,
so the verse says in במדבר, Bamidbar, אלה תעשו להשם במועדיכם. eleh
ta'asu l'Hashem b'mo'adeichem. These, which is at the end of all of
the קרבנות korbanot in פנחס, Pinchas, you should do in their time.
So it uses the word מועד, mo'ed, it also connects all the
קרבנות korbanot to one another, so therefore to the תמיד Tamid and
so on. So everything like the תמיד Tamid overrides שבת Shabbat and
טומאה. tumah. מנין לרבות עומר והקרב עמו שתי הלחם והקרב עמהן minayin
l'rabot omer v'hakarev imo shtei halechem v'hakarev imahen? Now in פנחס Pinchas
it doesn't mention the עומר omer and the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem.
It mentions the עומר, omer, שתי הלחם shtei halechem in אמור. Emor.
It's interesting, פנחס Pinchas is much more about the מוספים, Musafim, אמור
Emor is more about the מועדים Moadim with a focus not on
the מוספים Musafim but a little bit on how they're celebrated out
of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash like taking of the לולב lulav
and the sitting in the סוכה sukkah and also with a little
bit of an emphasis on the agricultural things like the עומר omer
and the שתי הלחם shtei halechem which is not in פנחס. Pinchas.
So it's interesting to note the differences of emphasis of פנחס Pinchas
and אמור. Emor. So אמור Emor mentions the שתי הלחם shtei halechem
and it mentions the עומר omer and the קרבנות korbanot that come
with it. A lamb comes with the עומר, omer, the two lambs
of the שלמים shelamim come with the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. How
do you know those override שבת Shabbat and טומאה? tumah? Because it
doesn't say there תעשו במועדיכם, ta'asu b'mo'adeichem, that's in פנחס. Pinchas. So
how do you know those things override שבת Shabbat and טומאה? tumah?
תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, that's why the פסוק pasuk says at the
end of אמור Emor this other פסוק, pasuk, וידבר משה את מועדי
השם. vayidaber Moshe et mo'adei Hashem. משה Moshe spoke the מועדים, Moadim,
so they're all called מועד mo'ed fixed time, they're all equated to
one another. הכתיב קבע מועד לכולם. hichtiv kava mo'ed lekulam. They all
have a fixed time, they all override שבת, Shabbat, they all override
טומאה. tumah. So now we have רבי Rebbe saying that the עומר
omer overrides שבת. Shabbat. Now that's not a big point because obviously
that's much more simply talking about the bringing of the עומר omer
than the cutting of the עומר, omer, but let's see what the
גמרא Gemara does with that. למאי l'mai? What is his point to
learn from here that the עומר omer overrides שבת? Shabbat? אילימא להקרבה,
ileima l'hakravah, if it's talking about bringing it, שתי הלחם בני הקרבה
נינהו shtei halechem bnei hakravah ninhu? You can't be talking about burning
it on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, offering it on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, because
you don't do that to... by the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem and
the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem is חמץ, chametz, right? You bring the
animals on the מזבח, mizbeach, you don't bring them on the מזבח.
mizbeach. So אלא פשיטא ela peshita to when he's talking that the
שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem overrides שבת, Shabbat, he's not talking about bringing
them, what's he talking about? He's talking about preparing them. לתחינה le-tchinah
the grinding, הקדה hakadah the sifting, so that's what overrides שבת Shabbat
for the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem because the bringing of the שתי
הלחם Shtei HaLechem is no מלאכה. melachah. וודכוותיה ve-dachvetei גבי עומר, gabei
Omer, so by analogy what overrides שבת Shabbat by the עומר? Omer?
לקצירה le-ktzirah the cutting, the preparing of it, וקא דחי את השבת.
ve-ka dachi et HaShabbat. So by analogy the same way the שתי
הלחם Shtei HaLechem means the preparing of the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem
overrides שבת, Shabbat, by the עומר Omer it means the preparing of
the עומר Omer overrides שבת Shabbat and here again you see that
רבי Rebbi holds cutting of the עומר Omer overrides שבת. Shabbat. No,
no, no, we said before he didn't. But that's what we're trying
to emphasize our problem. Don't try to get out of it and
tell me all these hold that the bringing overrides שבת. Shabbat. I
can prove to you from here that רבי Rebbi holds even the
cutting of the עומר Omer overrides שבת. Shabbat. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, you're wrong. לא. lo. They changed the word אלא ela
to לא lo because it's really... לא, lo, no, that's not the
way to read the ברייתא. braita. עומר להקרבה. Omer le-hakravah. When it
says the עומר Omer overrides שבת, Shabbat, it's not talking about the
cutting, it's talking about the bringing. ושתי הלחם, ve-Shtei HaLechem, and the
שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem is not the early stages of the preparation,
which might be analogous to the harvesting of the עומר, Omer, but
it's לאפיה le-afiyah the baking of the שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem. Now
it's not just that it's a later stage, it's also trying to
be consistent with this idea that if anything could be done beforehand,
it has to be done beforehand. So the גמרא Gemara wants to
say according to רבי, Rebbi, why does it not override שבת? Shabbat?
Because it's possible to cut earlier and it would still be כשר.
kasher. So then it says true, what aspect of the שתי הלחם
Shtei HaLechem could not be done earlier? You can grind it earlier,
you can... when you bring it on שבת Shabbat you don't have
to do a מלאכה. melachah. What aspect cannot be done earlier? It
says baking. Why could baking not be done earlier? Why not bake
the bread the day before? Won't be fresh but it won't be
פסול. pasul. So why won't it be כשר? kasher? So we're going
to say... the baking, right, the baking creates the... makes it קדוש.
kadosh. And if it makes it קדוש, kadosh, then you have to
wait to the next day, it's פסול בלינה, pasul bi-linah, it becomes
invalid with the next day. So therefore only the baking is done
on the day. And again the point is to underscore the principle
that if it can be כשר kasher otherwise, you cannot do it
on שבת. Shabbat. I guess they must have said they didn't put
it in a כלי שרת kli sharet beforehand. Right. Well, right, so
let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says, well, כלי שרת
אין מקדשין אלא לדעת kli sharet ein mekadeshin ela le-da'at and might
not... anyway even if they did it might not have mattered, but
yes that's the question. So the גמרא Gemara says, ושתי הלחם לאפיה.
ve-Shtei HaLechem le-afiyah. וכסבר רבי תנור מקדש. ve-kasavar Rebbi tanur mekadesh. And
רבי Rebbi holds that the תנור tanur sanctifies it and that's why
there was no other choice but to do it on שבת. Shabbat.
אי אפיה מאתמול פסלה בלינה. ei afiyah me-etmol pasla bi-linah. And therefore
if you had done it the day before it would become פסול.
pasul. So this is a really fascinating גמרא Gemara because clearly all
of the evidence points to the fact that even though you can
cut it בדיעבד be-di'avad afterwards, that nevertheless we allow it to override
שבת Shabbat because that's the מצוה. mitzvah. And nevertheless because the גמרא
Gemara is committed to the idea that if it could be done
without violating שבת, Shabbat, you do it without violating שבת, Shabbat, it
creates this position that according to רבי Rebbi it does not override
שבת. Shabbat. Now again to qualify that on the one hand the
גמרא Gemara does not question the point which is very much true
of all קרבנות, korbanot, that once it overrides שבת, Shabbat, then you
can finish up the whole thing. So once you slaughter the קרבן
korban like the פסח Pesach or the תמיד Tamid or whatever, you
do the whole thing on שבת, Shabbat, you burn the אימורים imurim
etc. The question here is that when... do I need to, can
I start by violating שבת? Shabbat? Then the גמרא Gemara comes says
no, actually כשר, kasher, if it's כשר kasher some other way, bring
it that other way without violating שבת, Shabbat, which is interesting because
we normally you know have a sense that there is not so
much of that hesitancy of שבת Shabbat in the מקדש Mikdash and
here we're saying if you could start it without violating שבת Shabbat
then you can't start the process by violating שבת. Shabbat. The other
thing however that is bizarre is you could have easily resolved this
problem by saying just because it's כשר kasher the following day does
not mean it's כשר kasher the previous day. I mean you know
if you think about let's say a ברית מילה, brit milah, right,
you can't do it until the eighth day in the morning, but
after then you can do it later, right? But anytime earlier doesn't
count. So you could have easily said that רבי Rebbi holds it's
כשר kasher the following day but the reason it still overrides שבת
Shabbat is because he might hold anytime earlier than ממחרת השבת, mi-macharat
HaShabbat, you know than the sixteenth of ניסן, Nisan, is by definition
no longer in the period of bringing the עומר Omer and by
definition it's no good. It's very strange the גמרא Gemara doesn't suggest
that. I guess I'm assuming they didn't put it in a כלי
שרת kli sharet beforehand. Right. Well right, so let's take a look.
The cutting of it? The גמרא Gemara never thinks that if you
cut earlier that שבועות Shavuot would begin earlier although you're right the
פסוקים pesukim do say מהחל חרמש בקמה תחל לספור. me-hachel chermesh ba-kamah
tachel lispor. So but take it more on the other side. Like
if you cut it late then you're making the... No, that's only
if you cut it... oh, but not if you cut it late
in the day. The day is the same halachic day, right? It's
very bizarre just because we say it's כשר kasher later that day,
it is no reason to think that that translates into כשר kasher
earlier or even כשר kasher on a different day, right? I wish
it would be earlier, it's a very interesting point, I don't know.
Okay so let's finish up the פרק. perek. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this... okay... וסבר רבי... ve-savar Rebbi... וסבר רבי תנור מקדש,
v'savar Rabbi tanur mikadesh, does רבי Rabbi really hold that the תנור
tanur is what sanctifies the שתי הלחם? shtei halechem? והתניא, vehatanya, it
was taught in a ברייתא, braisa, כבשי עצרת אין מקדשין את הלחם
אלא בשחיטה, kivshei atzeret ein makdishin et halechem ela bishchita, that the
lambs of שבועות Shavuot sanctified the bread when they are slaughtered. כיצד,
keytzad, how is this true? שחטן לשמן, shachtan l'shman, if you slaughtered
the lambs of עצרת atzeret for the right purpose, וזרק דמן לשמן,
v'zarak daman l'shman, and you threw the blood for the right purpose,
everything you did correctly, then קידש הלחם, kidesh halechem, the לכם lechem
is sanctified. שחטן שלא לשמן וזרק דמן שלא לשמן, shachtan shelo l'shman
v'zarak daman shelo l'shman, let's say you did it half right and
half not right. You slaughtered them correctly but you didn't sprinkle the
blood correctly. Then לא קידש הלחם, lo kidesh halechem, וזרק דמן שלא
לשמן לא קידש הלחם, v'zarak daman shelo l'shman lo kidesh halechem, the
bread is not sanctified. שחטן לשמן... shachtan l'shman... both were incorrect, that's
another easy case. Both were לא לשמן, lo l'shman, the bread is
not sanctified. Now what does it happen half and half? שחטן לשמן
וזרק דמן שלא לשמן, shachtan l'shman v'zarak daman shelo l'shman, you started
on the right path, you שחטן shechted it correctly but the זריקה
zrika was not correct. So קדוש ואינו קדוש דברי רבי. kadosh v'eino
kadosh divrei rabbi. It's half קדוש. kadosh. The גמרא Gemara discusses what
that half means. Does it mean it's קדוש kadosh but you can't
eat it? What exactly does this limbo status mean? רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון אומר לעולם אינו קדוש עד שישחט לשמן ויזרק דמן לשמן. Rabbi
Elazar b'rabbi Shimon omer le'olam eino kadosh ad sheyishchat l'shman v'yizrok daman
l'shman. No, until you do both stages, the שחיטה shechita and the
זריקה, zrika, it doesn't get its קדושה. kidusha. It's not half, it's
zero. Now regardless of that and without figuring out what that half
stage means, we see that רבי Rabbi holds the slaughtering of the
lamb makes the bread sanctified and presumably that means that until that
point it can be redeemed and until that point if you wait
overnight it does not become invalid. So how can we say that
it's the baking of it that makes it sanctified to the point
that you cannot let it stay overnight? I don't understand, I don't
see the question.
Say it again.
Here we're saying that the slaughtering of the lamb sanctifies the שתי
הלחם. shtei halechem. We're talking about the לכם, lechem, the bringing of
the שתי עצרת. shtei atzeret.
No, not the לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, the שתי הלחם.
shtei halechem. כבשי עצרת, kivshei atzeret, the bringing of lambs of...
our question was with the לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. No, it was
by the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, שתי הלחם shtei halechem is דוחה
שבת.
doche shabbos. Okay. So how can you say the תנור tanur sanctifies
the bread? Here we're saying the slaughtering of the lamb sanctifies the
bread. ואמר רב נחמן, v'amar Rav Nachman, Rav Nachman said הוקבע ולא
הוקבע קאמר. hukva v'lo hukva ka'amar. We did not, you're right, when
it says the slaughtering of the lamb sanctifies, that word sanctifies was
imprecise. The sanctification came from the time it was baked in the
oven and from that stage on it cannot be redeemed, from that
stage on if it stays overnight it becomes פסול. pasul. So what
happens by the slaughtering of the lamb? The slaughtering of the lamb
establishes the lambs and the bread as one unit. You'll remember, right,
that there's all question about are they treated as one unit and
if one becomes פסול pasul can you use the other and so
on. And the sprinkling of the blood then makes the bread permissible
to be eaten. So the defining of them as a unit comes
through the slaughtering and the bringing of the lambs, but actually the
sanctity occurred already at the time of the oven. Okay, so we're
going to, you know, we could unpack that a little bit more
but we won't. So again to point out what the relevance of
all of this is, it's that the גמרא Gemara is really making
a point, which it's really, you know, not in the text but
it's in the sort of that the גמרא's Gemara emphasis in a
way about its principle about what can override שבת shabbos or not
in the מקדש. mikdash. That the גמרא Gemara thinks that if a
beginning of a process, even a process that's done in the מקדש
mikdash and even a process that's supposed to be done today, but
if the beginning of the process can start not on שבת, shabbos,
it cannot start on שבת. shabbos. And because of that the גמרא
Gemara says that when if the עומר omer in theory could be
brought before, could be cut earlier, you are not allowed to cut
it on שבת. shabbos. And when it comes to let's say the
שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, the only thing you can do on שבת
shabbos is the baking because the baking couldn't be done earlier. What
about the לחם הפנים? lechem hapanim? Same thing, I have to think
about it, but the same thing. Whatever could be done earlier has
to be done earlier even if the מצוה mitzvah is today. The
only thing that can be done today on שבת shabbos to start
the process is something that could not be done earlier. And that
again is quite fascinating but again the flip side of it is
when the process does is allowed to begin then you can finish
it even on שבת. shabbos. So and again to point out that
even within that principle one could easily have distinguished and said that
although אמר שמעון רבי omar Shimon Rabbi says it's קצר katzar the
following day, there was no reason to assume that meant that it
was קצר katzar the previous day. And therefore the whole conclusion of
the גמרא Gemara is a little strange, to easily have gotten out
of it by saying the previous day was no good. Anyway with
this we'll end, הדרן עלך רבי ישמעאל, hadran alach rabbi yishmael, and
we'll start on שבת shabbos with a new פרק. perek.